Thousands of patients every year lose their lives due to liver and oral cancer. Our best way to help these patients is to perform early detection and diagnoses of these diseases. So how do we detect these diseases today, and can artificial intelligence help? In patients who, unfortunately, are suspected of these diseases, an expert physician first orders very expensive medical imaging technologies such as fluorescent imaging, CTs, MRIs, to be performed. Once those images are collected, another expert physician then diagnoses those images and talks to the patient. As you can see, this is a very resource-intensive process,
Cada año, miles de pacientes pierden la vida a causa del cáncer hepático u oral. La mejor forma de ayudar a estos pacientes es realizar un diagnóstico precoz de esas enfermedades. ¿Cómo las detectamos hoy y cómo la inteligencia artificial puede ayudar? Cuando se sospecha que el paciente tiene alguna de estas enfermedades, un médico especialista pide tecnologías de escaneo muy caras como la captación de imágenes por fluorescencia, los TAC o las RM. Una vez que se obtienen las imágenes, otro médico especialista hace el diagnóstico y habla con el paciente. Como pueden ver, es un proceso que requiere de muchos recursos,
requiring both expert physicians, expensive medical imaging technologies, and is not considered practical for the developing world. And in fact, in many industrialized nations, as well. So, can we solve this problem using artificial intelligence? Today, if I were to use traditional artificial intelligence architectures to solve this problem, I would require 10,000 -- I repeat, on an order of 10,000 of these very expensive medical images first to be generated. After that, I would then go to an expert physician,
médicos especialistas y costosos equipos de diagnóstico por escáner, y no se considera práctico para los países en desarrollo. De hecho, ni siquiera en muchos países desarrollados. ¿Podemos resolver este problema con la inteligencia artificial? Hoy, si fuera a utilizar arquitecturas de inteligencia artificial tradicionales para resolver este problema, necesitaría obtener 10 000... Repito, cerca de 10 000 de estos costosos aparatos médicos, y eso para empezar. Luego, consultaría a un especialista,
who would then analyze those images for me. And using those two pieces of information, I can train a standard deep neural network or a deep learning network to provide patient's diagnosis. Similar to the first approach, traditional artificial intelligence approaches suffer from the same problem. Large amounts of data, expert physicians and expert medical imaging technologies. So, can we invent more scalable, effective and more valuable artificial intelligence architectures to solve these very important problems facing us today? And this is exactly what my group at MIT Media Lab does. We have invented a variety of unorthodox AI architectures to solve some of the most important challenges facing us today in medical imaging and clinical trials. In the example I shared with you today, we had two goals. Our first goal was to reduce the number of images required to train artificial intelligence algorithms. Our second goal -- we were more ambitious, we wanted to reduce the use of expensive medical imaging technologies to screen patients. So how did we do it? For our first goal, instead of starting with tens and thousands of these very expensive medical images, like traditional AI, we started with a single medical image. From this image, my team and I figured out a very clever way to extract billions of information packets. These information packets included colors, pixels, geometry and rendering of the disease on the medical image. In a sense, we converted one image into billions of training data points, massively reducing the amount of data needed for training. For our second goal, to reduce the use of expensive medical imaging technologies to screen patients, we started with a standard, white light photograph, acquired either from a DSLR camera or a mobile phone, for the patient. Then remember those billions of information packets? We overlaid those from the medical image onto this image, creating something that we call a composite image. Much to our surprise, we only required 50 -- I repeat, only 50 -- of these composite images to train our algorithms to high efficiencies. To summarize our approach, instead of using 10,000 very expensive medical images, we can now train the AI algorithms in an unorthodox way, using only 50 of these high-resolution, but standard photographs, acquired from DSLR cameras and mobile phones, and provide diagnosis. More importantly, our algorithms can accept, in the future and even right now, some very simple, white light photographs from the patient, instead of expensive medical imaging technologies. I believe that we are poised to enter an era where artificial intelligence is going to make an incredible impact on our future. And I think that thinking about traditional AI, which is data-rich but application-poor, we should also continue thinking about unorthodox artificial intelligence architectures, which can accept small amounts of data and solve some of the most important problems facing us today, especially in health care. Thank you very much. (Applause)
que analizaría esas imágenes. Y con esos dos datos, puedo entrenar una red neuronal profunda o una red de aprendizaje profundo para diagnosticar a los pacientes. Parecido al primer enfoque, los enfoques tradicionales de IA tienen el mismo problema. Gran cantidad de datos, especialistas y equipos profesionales de escaneo. ¿Podemos entonces inventar arquitecturas de inteligencia artificial más escalables, efectivas y más útiles para resolver estos problemas a los que hoy nos enfrentamos? Esto es exactamente lo que hace mi grupo en el MIT Media Labs. Hemos inventado una variedad de arquitecturas de IA no convencionales para resolver algunos de los retos más importantes que enfrentamos hoy en los escáneres y estudios clínicos. En el ejemplo que compartí hoy teníamos dos objetivos. El primero era reducir el número de imágenes necesarias para entrenar a los algoritmos de inteligencia artificial. Con el segundo fuimos más ambiciosos, queríamos reducir el uso de estos costosos equipos de tecnología para escaner los pacientes. ¿Cómo lo hicimos? Para el primer objetivo, en vez de comenzar con decenas de miles de estas costosas imágenes, como la IA tradicional, comenzamos con una sola imagen médica. De esta imagen, mi equipo y yo encontramos una manera ingeniosa de extraer miles de millones de paquetes de información. Estos paquetes incluían colores, píxeles, geometría y la representación de la enfermedad en la imagen de diagnóstico. Es decir, convertimos una imagen en miles de millones de puntos de datos, reduciendo enormemente la cantidad de datos necesarios para el entrenamiento. Para el segundo objetivo, para reducir el uso de los costosos escáneres para examinar pacientes comenzamos con una fotografía estándar con luz natural tomada con una cámara DSLR o con el teléfono del paciente. ¿Recuerdan esos miles de millones de paquetes de información? Superpusimos esos paquetes de la imagen de diagnóstico sobre esta imagen, creando lo que llamamos una imagen compuesta. Para nuestra sorpresa, solo necesitamos 50, repito, solo 50 de esas imágenes compuestas para entrenar a los algoritmos con gran eficiencia. Para resumir nuestro enfoque, en lugar de utilizar 10 000 costosas imágenes de diagnóstico, hoy podemos entrenar a los algoritmos de IA de un modo poco ortodoxo, usando solo 50 de estas fotos de alta definición pero estándares, tomadas con cámaras DSLR y teléfonos, y establecer un diagnóstico. Más importante aun, nuestros algoritmos pueden aceptar, en el futuro o incluso hoy, algunas fotos muy sencillas y estándares del paciente, en lugar de los costosos equipos de diagnósticos por escáner. Creo que estamos preparados para entrar en una nueva era en la que la inteligencia artificial incidirá increíblemente en nuestro futuro. Y, pensando en la IA tradicional, que es rica en datos pero ineficiente en su utilización, deberíamos seguir pensando en arquitecturas de IA no convencionales que aceptan poca cantidad de datos y resuelven algunos de los problemas más importantes de hoy en día, especialmente en el sector de la salud. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)